Register of the Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha collection,
1909-1978
2001C62
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, minutes, serial issues, and photographs, relating to Russian émigré schools in Harbin, China.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials relating to the Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha (male and female high schools subordinated to the Ministry of Finances, rather than the Ministry of Education, in Harbin, China). The photographs document the actual life of the schools, while the PRINTED MATTER and GENERAL series offer historical materials and documents relating to the activities of the schools' alumni association, formed in San Francisco in the 1950s.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russians--China.; Education--China.; Harbin (China).; China.; Russia.
Container List
- General File, 1955-1978 and undated. (Box 1)
  Charter, clippings, correspondence, lists, minutes of meetings, and subject file, relating primarily to the founding and activities of the alumni association of the schools, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General. (Folder 1: 1)
    Indexed file of materials collected by Alex N. Kniazeff, collector
  - Charter (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 1: 3)
  - Correspondence. (Folder 1: 4)
    Much of the correspondence is with N. P. Avtonomov and N. N. Lebedeff, one-time head of the alumni association
  - Lists of members of the alumni association (Folder 1: 5)
  - Minutes of meetings. (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes notices of meetings, notes on matters discussed and a press release on a general meeting
  - Subject file - Icons (Folder 1: 7)
- Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha File, 1956-1974. (Box 1-2)
  Issues #1-12 of the periodical Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha, edited by N. P. Avtonomov, and an unnumbered issue of the title dedicated to the Kharbinskii politekhnicheskii institut (1970)
  - #1-3 (1956) (Folder 1: 8)
  - #4-6 (1957-1959) (Folder 1: 9)
  - #7-9 (1960-1969) (Folder 1: 10)
  - #10-12 (1970-1974) (Folder 1: 11)
  - Unnumbered issue (1970) dedicated to the Kharbinskii politekhnichewskii institut (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Photographs, ca. 1909-1930. (Folder 2: 2)
  Album of prints depicting the life of students in the schools, individual teachers and officials of the schools (including N. V. Borzov), and groups of graduates